A Guide to the John Palmer Fishwick Papers, 1971-1981
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
John Palmer Fishwick Papers, 1971-1981
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1987-053
7 Cubic Feet; 5 boxes
The papers include speeches; testimonies for the Senate Committee on Energy and Natural Resources, and other federal committees; minutes; memoranda; Legislation-status reports; and reports and other materials from the Organization of American Railroads created or collected by John Palmer Fishwick. Materials date from 1971-1981.
Fishwick, John Palmer, 1916-2010
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Source of Acquisition
The John Palmer Fishwick Papers were donated to Special Collections and University Archives in 1987.
Biographical Note
John Palmer Fishwich was born in Roanoke, Virginia, in 1916. He graduated from Roanoke College and Harvard Law School. After several years in a private law firm and then in the military, he went to work for Norfolk and Western in 1945. Duriig his long career with the railroad company, he spent a ten year term as President and Chief Executive Officer of the Norfolk and Western Railway Company from 1970-1980. He retired in 1981, but not before aiding in talks that led to the merger and formation of the Norfolk Southern Corporation. He was also a member of the Board of Directors for the Virginia Foundation for the Humanities. Fishwick died in Roanoke in August 2010 at the age of 93.
Scope and Content
The papers include speeches; testimonies for the Senate Committee on Energy and Natural Resources, and other federal committees; committee/board minutes; memoranda; and reports created or collected by John Palmer Fishwick. Materials date from 1971-1981.
The majority of the collection consists of speeches and talks given by Fishwick between 1971 and 1981 at professional conferences, meetings, schools,graduations, dedications, and other events. The collection also contains testimony before the Senate, reports and minutes from board/committee meetings, newspaper articles and clippings, and professional memos.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series by material type:
Series I. Speeches and Talks
Series II. Statements and Testimony
Series III. Conferences and Board Meetings and Reports
Series IV. Memos, Articles, and Clippings
Files within each series are in chronological order, with undated materials at the end.
Rights Statement for Archival Description
The guide to the John Palmer Fishwick Papers by Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, is licensed under a CC0 (https://creativecommons.org/share-your- work/public-domain/cc0/).
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Railroad
People:
Fishwick, John Palmer, 1916-2010
Contents List
- Series I. Speeches and Talks, 1972-1981, n.d.
  - JPF Speech Before Twelfth Annual Conference, March 15, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Fishwick--Speeches, September 27, 1972-May 15, 1973, October 10, 1973-May 8, 1974, April 30-October 10, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
  - JPF Speech-Dedication Water Treatment Plant, November 15, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - JPF Remarks-NY Society of Security Analysts, Inc., January 8, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - JPF Speech at Annual Meeting of Traffic Club, January 14, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Remarks by JPF on "The Forum" at the Annual Joint Meeting of TMMF-RPI, April 8, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - JPF Address before 55th Membership Meeting, April 18, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Remarks by JPF at Annual Meeting of the Great Lake Conference, July 15, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Remarks of JPF on Annual Meeting of the Great Lakes Conference of Public Utilities Commissioner, July 15, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Luncheon Speech before Annual Meeting of Railway Tie Association, October 16, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Remarks by JPF for the 1976 Industrial Transportation Conference, January 8, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Remarks of JPF 30th Virginia Feed Convention and Nutrition Conference, February 19, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Transportation Association of America 1976 National Transportation Institute, March 3, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Address by JPF Public Forum on "Humanistic Education: The Public and the Changing College", April 22, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Fallon Park Elementary School, May 6, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Remarks by JPF before Annual Meeting of American Railroad Development Association, May 10, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Remarks by JPF before Annual Meeting of Stockholders, May 13, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Remarks by JPF before the American Institute of Mining, June 4, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Remarks by John Fishwick at Seminar of AAR Cash Analysts, September 14, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Delta Nu Alpha Transportation Fraternity, October 14, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Remarks by John PF at Annual Meeting of Delta Nu Alpha Transportation Fraternity, October 14, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Class at Northwestern University, November 1, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Delaware and Hudson Railway Company Delaware and Hudson Railway Company, May 11, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual Meeting of Stockholders, May 12, 1977, May 11, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Fishwick--Speech, May 25, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Commencement Address, June 17, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Address before AAR-RPI luncheon, October 13, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 55th Annual Conference of Association Railroad Editors, October 19, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Before Annual Meeting, March 21, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Speech before Annual Dinner of the Greater Bluefield Chamber of the Commerce, April 14, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Roanoke at Panel Discussion, April 20, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Talk before VPI Seminar, December 5, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Talk at News Maker Banquet, January 26, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Talk before Annual meeting of NU Stockholders, May 10, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Talk before Richmond Society of Security, October 4, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - JPF talk before Antitrust and Trade Regulation Law, October 11, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Introduction of Senator Sam Ervin Jr., October 19, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Talk prepared for Conference on "Financing the Capital Needs of Transportation Industries", February 19, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - NU Annual Meeting of Stockholders, May 8, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Speech before St. Louis Railway Club Missouri Athletic Club Man of the Year Banquet, May 15, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Talk before Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers-Southeast Regional Meeting, June 25, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Talk before Southeastern Division of the Association of America, November 23, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Talk before Annual Meeting of Roanoke Valley Chamber of Commerce, January 6, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Lynchburg College-Gifford Lecture, April 6, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - Washington, DC. AAR's "Coal and the Railroads" briefing for News Media [missing doc], April 22, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Omni International-Norfolk, 61st Annual Banquet of Hampton Roads Maritime Association, May 7, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Baltimore Hotel, NYC "Dynamics of World Coal Trade-A Buyer Seller Symposium", June 11, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Physical Distribution Panel Talk (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Firewall (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Remarks by JPF at the Executive Seminar Loyola College (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Shenandoah Life Insurance Co. Duplicate Speeches/Statements (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Series II. Statements and Testimony, 1974-1980, n.d.
  - Affadavit-Charles Shannon, Hearing, June 14, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - JPF Statement, January 14, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Statement of JPF to the Finance Company, April 6, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Statement before Virginia Senate Committee on Commerce and Labor, January 31, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Statement before Transportation and Commerce Subcommittee of the Interstate and Foreign Commerce of the US House of Representatives, May 31, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Statement before Transportation and Commerce Subcommittee, May 31, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Testimony for Senate Committee on Energy and Natural Resources, September 19, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Statement Supporting President Carter, October 29, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Statement before Interstate and Foreign Commerce Committee of the US House of Representatives (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Statement of Fisherwick before Transportation and Capital Outlay Subcommittees of Virginia house of Representatives (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Testimony before House Merchant Marine and Fishers Committee (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Series III. Conferences and Board Meetings and Reports, 1971-1977, n.d.
  - Conference Board: 001, 1971-1980 (Box 1)
  - Fishwick-Seminar Meeting, Southern Coals Conference Inc., February 1971, February 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Report-Oak Island Terminal, May 4, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - AAR Board of Directors-Executive Committee: Notices, Dockets, and Minutes of Meetings (AAR Vol. Nos. 4-5, 7-12) (Box 4)
  - AAR Board of Directors--Executive Committee, Notices/Dockets and Minutes of Meetings (Vol. Nos. 13-16) (Box 1)
  - Economic Opportunities (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Erie Lackawanna Railway Co., Presidential Office File (Vol. No. 2) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Railroad Annual Report Form A (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Conference Board YAMA Conference (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Series IV. Memos, Articles, and Clippings, 1972-1977, n.d.
  - Memorandum-Cox, February 14, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Scranton Times, June 10, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - News Release-Delaware and Hudson Railway Company, May 25, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Locomotive Engineer Newspaper (Vol. 108, No. 23) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Memorandum-McNamee and Cash Statement (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Magazines (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - JPF Article "The Chief Executive and the Media" (Box 5, Folder 7)